<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Peri ydroposias: or, a discourse of waters their qualities, and effects diæteticall, pathologicall, and pharmacaiticall. By Tobias Whitaker, doctor in physicke of Norwich.</title>
            <author>Whitaker, Tobias, d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101856</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837659</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837659</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1997</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1997)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1016:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Peri ydroposias: or, a discourse of waters their qualities, and effects diæteticall, pathologicall, and pharmacaiticall. By Tobias Whitaker, doctor in physicke of Norwich.</title>
                  <author>Whitaker, Tobias, d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 159, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by A. Mathewes] for Iohn Grismond, at the signe of the Gunne in Ivie-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first two words of the title are in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hydrotherapy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mineral waters --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1997:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1997:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΠΕΡΙ ΥΔΡΟΠΟΣΙΑΣ: <hi>OR,</hi> A DISCOVRSE of WATERS: Their Qualities, and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects Diaeteticall, Patho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall, and Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macaiticall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> TOBIAS WHITAKER, <hi>Doctor</hi> in Phyſicke of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Iohn Griſmond,</hi> at the ſigne of the Gunne in Ivie-Lane. 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1997:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1997:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the firſt view this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject may ſeem light, ſimple, and ſcarce worth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; but whenas you have conſulted with your ſecond
<pb facs="tcp:1997:3"/>thoughts, you cannot but confeſſe, that our whole beeing in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the ſame, doth depend upon the right uſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of water, as being ſo neceſſary in meates and drinkes, as alſo in medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental compoſitions, which cannot but be a matter of very great conſequence, ſince no natural good
<pb facs="tcp:1997:3"/>can bee equall to life and health, which is loſt or injoyed by the ill diſpoſition of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ayre. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to offer a ſacrifice more grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and acceptable to my Countrey, and deareſt friends, I have indeavoured to wade throgh ſprings, pools, moats, moores, as alſo the ſea (which is the wombe of them
<pb facs="tcp:1997:4"/>all) And that I may guide both my ſelfe and others ſafely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver theſe Waſhes, no leſſe dangerous then the rocks and quick-ſands of the Ocean, therfore I have bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed a light from thoſe ancient guides which have ſteered the courſe ſo many hundreds of yeares without ſhipwracke. This ſtile and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod are anſwerable
<pb facs="tcp:1997:4"/>to my intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is onely to informe ſtrangers in our art, without prejudice to the ſame, conſidering that I have inabled no man any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then to defend himſelfe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his health by the choice of a whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſituation in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of water, which is ſo uſefull in the whole courſe of his life, and ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,
<pb facs="tcp:1997:5"/>if proceeding from an unwholſome earth, whether uſed in medicament or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et: For this cauſe I have clad my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in ſuch robes as are moſt faſhiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the place and perſons, to whom it is chiefely intended: and although <hi>Suum cuique pulchrum,</hi> bee the common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe, and that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans owne childe
<pb facs="tcp:1997:5"/>ſeemes to himſelfe the faireſt, howſoere ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled; yet in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (whatſoever o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe my affection is) I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admire beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in others more lovely then my owne; and will bee bold to taxe cenſorious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, chiefely in ſuch as never yet were fruitful themſelves: not knowing but that their owne birthes may prove as mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous
<pb facs="tcp:1997:6"/>and deformed as any; and alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who out of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentious ſpirit ſhall oppoſe any poſitive truth, or indeavour to raiſe their owne names by the defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming others more worthy then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: for example, who is ignorant of that ſubtle <hi>Argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius,</hi> as alſo with what malignity and contentious ſpirit he
<pb facs="tcp:1997:6"/>doth oppoſe the ſolid &amp; learned doctrine of <hi>Galen;</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there is a liberty of exception granted to all wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and hath beene practiſed by all both ancient and modern, as is extant in many volumes, where wee plainly ſee the ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler at foyles with the Maſter, and one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with another; which were a new la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb facs="tcp:1997:7"/>and would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire another tract to make particular demonſtration: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to avoyde all ſtrife, I have chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laboured to ſhews plainely the ancient opinions, practice, &amp; uſe of this ſubject, as it may conduce to the preſer vatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of health generation of ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and recover of the ſame; and from hence to teacl
<pb facs="tcp:1997:7"/>how dangerous it may be to forſake the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten roade or path, in which the ancient Worthies have ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walked ſo many ages, loſing our ſelus &amp; dangerouſly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leading others into unknowne wayes, which cannot but be doubtfull, how ever wee eſcape. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in thus doing I have given offence to any, tis beſide my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb facs="tcp:1997:8"/>or deſire; if otherwiſe I have not, then I have the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of my time and labour, which might have been more neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently ſpent: yet had I deſired to ſhew my ſelfe, rather then make good the juſt requeſts of my ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall friends, then J would have choſen another part, which I ſuppoſe might have beene better acted;
<pb facs="tcp:1997:8"/>but leſt the Gates ſhould exceede the Citie, I take my leave.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Tobias Whitaker,</hi> Doctor in Phyſicke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1997:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1997:9"/>
            <head>ΠΕΡΙ Υ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΔΡΟΠΟΣΙΑΣ.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ippocrates</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. de aere locis &amp; aquis, ſect. 3.</hi> Qui artem meadicam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequi volet, is primum quidem anni tempora in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> debet adhibere, quid horu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quid<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poſsit, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim quicqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habent ſimile ſed cum inter ſe plurimum differunt, tum etiam propter varias quae in eis contingunt mutationes.</note> adviſes ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly thoſe which will apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1997:10"/>to Artes, in the firſt place that they diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the times &amp; ſeaſons of the yere, with their altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and change, as alſo the faculties of waters<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. l. de aere loc. &amp; aq. cap. 1.</hi> Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vero negligentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſe circa aquaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultates cognoſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>das exhibere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit; que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim guſtu differunt et pondere ſic quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute aliae ab aliſs longe diſſentire videntur.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing much to the Diagnoſticke, Prognoſtick, and Curative part of Medicine, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth plainly in the foreſaid Book,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1997:10"/>and in his Booke<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>l. De ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. ſect. 6.</hi> ulceribus pleriſquè calidum an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni tempus magis quam hyems con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducit, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terquam ijs quaeſunt in capite ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctium.</note> 
               <hi>De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer.</hi> Since therefore there is ſuch neceſsitie, as alſo ſuch power in theſe to preſerve health, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a natural bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as alſo in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating diſeaſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arious formes, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he perdition and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uine of the beſt Conſtitution and Temper, it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth a Phyſician e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1997:11"/>ſpecially to ſtudie the nature and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of them and all others to take notice and ſtricktly obſerve them, ſo farre as in their nature they are good or bad for common uſe for by this meane they ſhall be abl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to prevent a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which other wiſe were inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1997:11"/>all diſeaſes and diſtempers are conveyed to us in our prinoiples of generation or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; to both which do chiefely concur the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts both by way of exiſtence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, and in both reſpects are Cauſes either of harmony or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pord in mixt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and are Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſically
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1997:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to foure (that is to ſay) materiall, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, efficient, and finall; medically into two, and they are <hi>per conſenſum medicorum</hi> divided generally into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. But becauſe external cauſes are prime &amp; more uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, therefore wee will chiefely explicat the nature
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1997:12"/>and condition of them, ſo farre as they tend to our purpoſe. External cauſes are ſuch as come from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and of theſe we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitute three orders, divine, cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall, and ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harie: But wee paſſe by the two former, and (to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toyde digreſsion) wee will bound our ſelves within
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1997:13"/>the limits of the later: and amongſt ſublunary cauſes, wee will princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally diſcourſe of<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hipp. ſect. 3. fol. 66.</hi> demceps ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro de aquis nobis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, &amp; quae mor boſae &amp; quae ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berrimae ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtant.</note> Waters, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly philoſophically, as elementary, but alſo medically, as they are corrupt or incorrupt;<note n="e" place="margin">Plurimum enim mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentiad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem conſert.</note> as a weighty matter in the government of our health. And of theſe wee will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1997:13"/>generally obſerve three differences (that is to ſay) aery ſuch as diſtill from the clouds, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marine, or ſuch as are contained in the Ocean &amp; parts adjoyning, third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly terrene, or ſuch as ariſe out of the Earth. Aery wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to rayne, or ſuch as come of Snowe, Haile, and Froſt;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1997:14"/>terreſtriall are ſuch as ſpring out of the Earth; &amp; they are either nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or healing; the noriſhing are ſuch as we call ſweet, potable, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the taſte. And of theſe are divers ſpecies, as of fountaines, mores, Standing pooles, rivers, &amp; the like. Medicall Waters are alſo diverſe, as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1997:14"/>from Mineralls of gold, ſilver, braſſe, Iron, Sulphure, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, Bitumen, &amp;c. Laſtly, Sea-water is ſuch as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and maritime partes adjoyning. And theſe are their generall differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. It behoveth now to diſcourſe of their natures &amp; qualities more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, as they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1997:15"/>are good or bad, healthfull, or mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bifical. Foraſmuch as water that is ſimple, pure, and without alien mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is ſo neceſſary for the preſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life, we wil firſt make a deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe which are ſet apart for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of man; and theſe are either ſuch as ſpring out
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1997:15"/>of wholſom earth, and of themſelves are ſimple, pure, and ſweet, or ſuch as fall from the cloudes, and by tranſmutation are made water; both which offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to our view. Thoſe therefore which ariſe out of the earth, and are pure altogether, and voyd of alien mixture, or ſuch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1997:16"/>mixture as cannot bee diſcovered by ſenſe (for they can bee knowne to us otherwiſe then by their conſiſtence, nature, ſpirits, and qualities, by wch wee will in order demonſtrat them) thoſe are ſuch wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as are moſt wholſome and fit to bee taken into the body, and ought to bee ſuch,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1997:16"/>as are without both ſapor and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. And if any object that paſſage of <hi>Hipp.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>li. de aeie loc. &amp; aq. ſect.</hi> 3. maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vero com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendantur quorum fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ad ſolis exortus, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertim aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vos decurru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t limpidiores enim &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni odoris le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves eſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt. <hi>Gal. cap.</hi> 3. maxime ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro laddare eas oporter quarum flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xiones ad ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisexortus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpunt &amp; preſertim ad aeſtivos, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ſptedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diores eſſe oderatas &amp; leves.</note> and <hi>Gal.</hi> in their booke <hi>de aere loc. &amp; aquis,</hi> where they ſay, that ſweet and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doriferous waters are to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended; it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that by ſweetneſſe is to be underſtood plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſſe, and ſuch
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1997:17"/>as are gratefull to the taſte; adde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that inſipidnes, is as it were the firſt degree of ſweetneſſe in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but that which pertaineth to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, is nothing elſe but a gentle ſmoothe vapour, w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> out any rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſmell, is ſaid to ſmell beſt, becauſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1997:17"/>it ought to be void both of odor and ſapor, as is above ſaid. Secondly, good and health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full water is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. cap. 3.</hi> hae enim dalces &amp; albae ſunt.</note> the ſmoothneſſe, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſame: For waters by now much more pure they are, by ſo much they are more ſmooth, cleare, and thin,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1997:18"/>and by reaſon of their<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hipp. l. 5. A ph. 26.</hi> aqua quae citò cale fit &amp; citò re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frigeratur leviſsima.</note> tenuitie and lightneſſe, are ſoone made hott by fire, and ſoone cooled by the impreſsion of the ayre; and the reaſon is rendred by <hi>Gal.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 5. Aph.</hi> Sed nunc levie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem dixit aquam quae ventrem non gravat, &amp; quae cito permeat.</note> not becauſe ſuch water is light in reſpect of weight, but becauſe it is without any ſenſible op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion in the ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle,<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 5. Ap. 26.</hi> primum quidem ſi ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> turbidae neque caeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae: deinde ſine<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in guſtu, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in odoratu, aliquam ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdam qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem prae ſe fert: tum &amp; illud, quod nunc <hi>Hip:</hi> dixit, ſi cito refri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geratur &amp; cale ſit: nam perſpicuum exiſtit talem eſſe bene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terabilem.</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:1997:18"/>when as the ſtomack is not troubled with the receipt of it, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo when it paſſeth quickly out of the body againe by u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine. Contrarily wee call that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ponderous, which doth not paſſe through the body ſpeedily, but is trobleſom to the ſtomacke, ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the taſte,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1997:19"/>and ſmell; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Hipp.</hi> would haue us under ſtand, that ſuch water as is ſoone hot &amp; cold, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of levitie, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie and cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to a ſuddaine and ſpeedy change or alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which in meate &amp; drinke wee call concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpoſition, ſuch as is eaſily
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1997:19"/>tranſmutated or concocted by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tricle, indowed with a propertie, and dedicated by nature to ſuch a uſe. But this deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription offereth an objection, and peradventure ſom will urge or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that raine water doth poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the ſame con ſtitution of limpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, tenuitie, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1997:20"/>levitie, and yet is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned by <hi>Gal.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. l. 4. de ſanit. tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end. cap: 6.</hi> Quan quam poteſt, qui volet, &amp; ex pluvia aqua id conficere, ipſe<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſi pluviam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarem, id ſuaderem, verum nec ipſam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo, &amp; nihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo eſt deteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ſiacceſsit.</note> as moſt unwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, either in diet or medicine, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth plainely in his diſcourſe of <hi>Oximel,</hi> and the manner of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament; affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the uſe of raine water not to bee approved, and that of it ſelfe it is worſt of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1997:20"/>eſpecially if it grow ſower &amp; corrupt. To which anſwer, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her our Maſter, nor any other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Phiſician doth miſlike or not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſuch water, becauſe it is cleare, hin, and light, or aſie of digeſtion, but becauſe of an apt diſpoſion, that raine water hath to putrifie
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1997:21"/>more ſpeedily the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other water. And in this reſpect is much different from the former, which is alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>Hipp:</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hip. de aere loc. aq. ſect. 3.</hi> hae enim dulces ſunt &amp; albae modicum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vinum ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re queunt, per hyemem calidae, per aeſtatem fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidae.</note> to bee hot in winter and cold ſummer, which by reaſon of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colation, through the profound and deepe parts of the earth by antiperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie is hotter in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1997:21"/>winter, and in fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie weather doth commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly wreak: For it receiveth alteration, both from the bowels of the earth throgh which it runneth, and alſo from the earthie ayre with which it is mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Fourthly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt fountaines and ſprings, from rocks or clifts, thoſe are ſaid to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1997:22"/>bee moſt health full and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome which flow through earth and ſand: the reaſon is, becauſe they are purified in their courſe, and by colation through ſuch a body of ſandie earth, they leave behind them their groſnes, and alien qualities, by which they doe infect, &amp; are made
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1997:22"/>by this colature much more whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. Fiftly, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers which are moved are more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, then thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat want motion from the ayre or winds, as wels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r other encloſed ſprings; becauſe open ſtreames are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urified continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by the wind and ayre, as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1997:23"/>by <hi>Ariſt.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Meteor. l. 3.</hi> Finis eſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere aeris et aquae com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motionem, ne nimia quiete pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſcant &amp; ne putredine ſua amman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia enecent.</note> in his diſcourſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> winds, affirming<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the end o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their generation is to cauſe commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the ayre and waters, leſt by qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et they ſhould pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie and deſtroy the creatures that live in them &amp; of them; Laſtly, the puritie of the ayre, fiſh and vegetals, demonſtrate, the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1997:23"/>wholſomneſſe of the water, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubritie for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe externall or internall. By this time we have taught what wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are principally to be elected, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their nature and difference, and how to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them; for although all are eſteemed whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome that we have
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1997:24"/>hitherto ſpoken of, according to ſome moderne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions (that is to ſay) brewed: Yet ſome are more healthfull then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſtand in need of leſſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſuppoſe it behoovefull that wee explicate the nature &amp; qualities of morbifical wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſuch as offend
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1997:24"/>in ſmell or taſte, or otherwiſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re neither repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed wholſome for meat or medicine.</p>
            <p>Aire and water may affect human bodies three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all wayes; firſt as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey are elements, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey may hurt both by their qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, and that <hi>per ſe</hi> immediatly, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mediatly <hi>per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens:</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:1997:25"/>Secondly, as aliment, for ſo by reſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſubſtance of the ayre is ſaid to nouriſh; water al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is ſaid to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, inſomuch that it ſerveth for the diſtribution of aliment into every part of the body, and may alſo nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in deed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Avicen. li 1. ſen. 2. doct. 2.</hi> Non autem dicimus qd. aqua non nutriat quia nutriens eſt illud quod eſt in poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſanguis.</note> of its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. For the uſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1997:25"/>of water is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary to nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, as meat and drinke, but alſo to life, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the ſame; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by ſome<note n="*" place="margin">Ranchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Patho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. ſect. 2. cap. 10.</note> is called <hi>vitae potus, ſalus corporis.</hi> Yet <hi>Gal.</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. li. 4. de vſu part. cap. 5.</hi> at enim in hac quoquè vena multa adhuc hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miditate te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nui et aquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa plenus eſt ſanguis: vocat autem ipſam <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> conceiveth and ſeemeth to perſwade others, that water doth not nouriſh <hi>per ſe,</hi> but inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1997:26"/>ſo farre as it is a <hi>vehiculum</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blood, and by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thinneſſe &amp; moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth convey th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blood into every part, for the nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing &amp; ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſame <hi>Avicen</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Avicen. li. 1. fen. 2. doct. 2. cap. 16.</hi> aqua vnum exiſtit ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meatorum: quae ſola in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter omnia e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementa ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ut in eo quod come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur &amp; bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatur, non ideo, ut nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triat, ſed quia nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrare fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, &amp; ejus rectificat ſubſt anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</note> alſo is o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame opinion water (ſaith he) is the ſole element indowed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Propertie recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1997:26"/>either in meat or drinke, to mixe and incorporate with it, and yet not nouriſh, but that it may rectifie the ſubſtance of nutrime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; make it penetrable, and in this reſpect is only ſaid to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. Thirdly, if they bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for by the uſe of medicall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1997:27"/>waters, as alſo the mutation of the aire, many diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are begotten, &amp; ſome are ſaid to be cur'd: &amp; for this cauſe the doctrine of aire, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to diet, but alſo to pathologie, and the curative part of medicine. In order therefore we will diſcourſe of ſuch waters as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1997:27"/>tend to the ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of health, Nevertheleſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I explicate their qualities and differences; give me leave to take up a queſtion by the way, which peradventure may ſeeme a ſmall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion, yet not ſo unneceſſary, but that it may bee wel argued in this place. The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1997:28"/>is whether aire or water have moſt power in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of health, or generating ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: They that prefer water firſt ground upon <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. li. 1. probl. 13.</hi> cur mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem aqua rum gravem eſſe affirme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> where the Philoſopher que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioneth, why the mutations of the water are more turbulent, then thoſe of the ayre; &amp; produceth rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1997:28"/>to prove it; for (ſaith hee) thoſe things which are able to make a ſtronger and fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer impreſsion, either by perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie or craſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, they ſeeme to bee more able, either to helpe or hurt; but water is more thicke then aire, and makes a longer ſtay in the body. Contrarily,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1997:29"/>
               <hi>Hippocrates</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth greater incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience in the ayre then in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and draweth his reaſon from the neceſsitie; for (ſaith hee) the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments of water may bee avoided, but the ambient ayre cannot bee ſhunned, but doth continually affect us, as doth appeare in his<note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>li.</hi> de aere. <hi>lo.</hi> et aquis <hi>li.</hi> de natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra humana. <hi>li.</hi> de natura pueri.</note> elegant
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1997:29"/>gradation, ſaying; ſuch as is the ayre, ſuch are the ſpirits, becauſe they are begotten of blood and ayre; ſuch as are the ſpirits, ſuch are the humours, as following the mature of them; ſuch as are the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, ſuch are the parts of the body, becauſe they are nouriſhed by them, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1997:30"/>To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, ſuch as is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> condition of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part, ſuch is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtate of the whole body. Hence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of ayre in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſervation and force in genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſickneſſe. But to ſet aſide the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, both of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</hi> and <hi>Hipp.</hi> the queſtion is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined thus; that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1997:30"/>the vitall and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall parts of the body are more &amp; ſooner affected by the ayre then by water, and that the naturall parts are more hurt by water then the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals: This being conceived, let us take notice of ſuch waters as doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the temper of the body, and are called morbifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1997:31"/>&amp; after what manner they are ſaid to be pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the life of man, ſome more, ſome leſſe, either internally or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally applied.</p>
            <p>Morbificall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are ſuch as are diſcoverd by ſenſe to have a taſte or ſmell; for thoſe that are healthfull and wholeſome, ought to have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1997:31"/>as is before ſaid in the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of wholſome water: Secondly, unwholſome wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are ſuch as have an offenſive taſte and ſtinking ſmell, ſuch as are grips, ditches, and channels from ſalt marſhes, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſhores, and theſe are ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſome as I need not urge au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1997:32"/>to prove it, yet becauſe I deſire to ſatisfie, take one learned ancient, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>inſtar omnium. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicen</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Avicen. Tract. 5. fol. 585.</hi> Aquae mali odoris coeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae tardam deſcentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſuam a ſtomaco, &amp; pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem cibi: &amp; ſitis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem augetur cum aquis huju ſmodi, &amp; virtus debilitatur, et quia ipſae non ſunt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae ſimplices, im o in hujuſmodi aquis eſt terreci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas plurima quare ex eis genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur humor a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> phlegmaticus vitreus, aut melancholicus, et prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter illud multiplica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aegritudines ſplenis in homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, qui plurimum bibunt de ipſis, &amp; acciden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t haemorroidas et hydropiſim propter mall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam complectionis hepatis inductam ab eis, &amp; mictum vrinae involuntarium propter malitia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> complectionis renum.</note> ſaith, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this nature that are ill ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, hinder the penetration &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of meat, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1997:32"/>by reaſon of their impuritie, beget viſcous phlegme, or melancholy, &amp; multiply Diſeaſes of the ſpleene, in ſuch manner, that thoſe which drink them often either by coaction or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morroids &amp; drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie by the imbeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and defect of the liver, obtained
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1997:33"/>by the ill qualitie of theſe waters, as alſo in voluntary mixtion by the ill diſpoſition of the reines; other wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters there are of moores, ſtanding pooles, and lakes, and theſe are ſaid to ſmell, eſpecially in the ſummer,<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. lib. de aere &amp; aq. cap. 3.</hi> quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> igitur pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtres ſunt, &amp; ſtabiles ac lacuſtres, eas neceſſe eſt aeſtate eſſe calidas, ac craſſas &amp; olentes, cum enim non deflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, ſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua pluvia ſemper nova inferatur et ſol urat ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas decolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res eſſe, &amp; pravas &amp; vitioſas.</note> which doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily come to paſſe for want of perflue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1997:33"/>are not as ſprings fitted of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as they are emptied, but ſuch as are augmented w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> new ſhowers of raine, &amp; exhaled again by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the ſun, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily they are groſſe diſcolored, unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant &amp; corrupt; in winter begetting corrupt phlegme, by their congealed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1997:34"/>diſpoſition, and in ſummer time vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and cholerick by aduſtion; in winter they are cold &amp; crude, and ſoon converted or tranſmutated into ice, and mixt with mud and ſnow, are not much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the dead ſea, or ſome Stygian lake; but howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they are very unwholſom, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1997:34"/>to the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ricle, and ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oth viciate and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orrupt the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ody, poyſon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aſſe, and deſtroy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he beſt temper; after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er <hi>Hippocrates</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hip. li. de aere loc. &amp; aq. ſect. 3.</hi> bibentibus autem lienes ſemper mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos eſſe &amp; compreſſos, ventres ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro duros &amp; tenues ac calidos hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meros vero &amp; iugula &amp; faciem extenuari, in lienem enim carnes coliqueſcunt ideo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſunt.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heweth: The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rinkers (ſaith he) of ſuch waters are alwayes or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inually affected with large ſpleens, hard, thin, and hot
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1997:35"/>bellies, ſhoulders, throat, &amp; face ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuat, the fleſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into ſpleen, and the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy waſted &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ravenous, and very thirſty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſiccity and drineſſe, both of the upper and lower venters: Adde alſo to theſe dropſies, and for the moſt part, ſuch
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1997:35"/>as are lethall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties of the bowels and fluxes of the belly, long quartane fevers, which by protra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of time ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, both particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the whole body, by which they periſh. And theſe diſeaſes w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are generated of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1997:36"/>ſuch corrupt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter happen in the ſummer: But thoſe of the winter, ſuch as fall upon young bodies, are inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the lungs &amp; madnes; to thoſe that are more ancient bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fevers, by reaſon of the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies:<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hip.</hi> mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieribus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò tumores proveniunt, &amp; pituita alba, vix concipiunt, &amp; cum dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultate foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus magnos &amp; tumidos pariunt, qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poſtea dum educan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſcunt, &amp; deteriores evadunt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que bona poſt partum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulieribus purgatio contingit.</note> women ſhall labour with phlegmatick ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1997:36"/>it ſhall bee difficult for them to conceive child, and if they prove pregnant, their births ſhal be large &amp; great, brought forth with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, and in ſhort time periſh; neither after child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth doe they purge according to the cuſtome of women: To chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that drinke
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1997:37"/>theſe waters chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ruptures, and to men warts and ulcers of the anckles, of ſuch a malignant condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as that they doe kill them in ſhort time, and in the meane while do wither them, &amp; make them ſeeme old or aged before their time: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over ſuch women ſeeme to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1997:37"/>to bee with child, and when the time of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry commeth, the tumor vaniſheth, and they are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether deceived, and their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions fruſtrated: To conclude, theſe and ſuch like are the common and ordinary effects of ſuch waters w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are of moors, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding pooles, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1997:38"/>the like, through which wee have ſpeedily waded, &amp; find them good for nothing, but the nouriſhing of venemous crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, eſpecially raw; &amp; therefore to bee ſhunned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat of <hi>Galen.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. de. ſanit. tuend. li. 1. cap. 11.</hi> covendae ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ſunt, quae ex ſtagnis hauriuntur et quae tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, &amp; quae malae olentes, &amp; quae ſalſae, deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in quibus qualit as aliqua guſtu deprehenditur.</note> Now let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine &amp; pierce the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1997:38"/>rocks<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hipp.</hi> ac hujuſmodi aqua ad quidvis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus eſſe cenſeo; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo loco eas quarum fontes in ſaxoſis locis ſunt (quas duras eſſe neceſſe eſt) aut ſi vbi calidae aquae exiſtunt aut ſerrum naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur, aut as, aut ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentum, aut aurum, aut ſulphur, aut al umen, aut bitumen, aut nitrum haec enim omnia caloris vi proveniunt.</note> &amp; mines, and taſte what li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor ſprings from them uſefull and ſafe, or morbifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. Theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that ſpring from rocks and clifts, are generally eſteemed crude &amp; hard, that is ſuch as paſſe not eaſily through the body, but are turbulent to the ſtrongeſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.<note n="*" place="margin">Hip ſect. 3</note> But thoſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1997:39"/>hot waters which ſpring from mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of gold, ſilver, braſſe, iron, ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, alume, bitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; the like; al theſe ſpring from the viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of heat, inſomuch, as ſome philoſophers have thought theſe to be the ſhewers of fire &amp; brimſtone, that deſtroyed So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and were thrown up by the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1997:39"/>force of ſome Earth-quake, out of ſome Aetna. But however they are ſuch as beget ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge diſeaſes in humane bodies<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hipp.</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que igitur ex hujuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di terra bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae aquae naſcuntur ſed durae &amp; aeſtuoſae, quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> per urinas non facile ferun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; alvi egeſtioni ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſantur.</note> and no good waters can ſpring from earth of this nature, for they are fervently hot and dry, they paſſe not eaſily by urine, and are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe from nature in common ege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1997:40"/>But becauſe we ſhall have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to explicate them more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in our fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe, therefore we will forſake the ſhore, and launch into the Ocean, where we chiefly obſerve the qualitie of ſea water, to bee ſalt, and not to bee drunke, but abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely prohibited
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1997:40"/>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hip ſect. 3</hi> ſalſae vero et indomitae &amp; durae, in totum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ut bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probandae.</note> to bee received into the body; for which cauſe I will haſten out, leſt <hi>Neptune</hi> inraged, ſhould force mee to drinke whether I will or not, <hi>at feſtina lente,</hi> let me before I take my leave, acquaint you with the will of my Maſter <hi>Hippocrates,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hip. ſect. 3</hi> at vero de aquis ſalſis propter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritiam fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntur qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam quod<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> alvum ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentur, cum maxime al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni repugne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in domitae e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ſunt et coquine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queunt; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ah eis venter poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us adſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur.</note> who would have it knowne, that for
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1997:41"/>want of skill in the nature &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of ſalt water many are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; For they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxe the belly, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they moſt of al conſtringe the ſame; beſides they are indomitable, quite out of the government of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny naturall power to bee concocted:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1997:41"/>Therefore Ile take my leave of them, &amp; returne to ſhore againe, and muſe a little concerning caeleſtiall water, or ſuch as falleth from the clouds in ſhewers, for theſe are alſo compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bificall waters, ſuch as principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tend to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1997:42"/>as alſo ſuch as comes from ſnow, and ice, or the like.<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal li. de aere lo. &amp; aq. cap. 4.</hi> aquae igitur pluviales leviſsimae et duteiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuiſsimae, &amp; ſplendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſsimae ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r, primum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ſol quod tenuiſsimum ac leviſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſt in aqua edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit ac ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum rapit.</note> Raine water in reſpect of ſubſtance, is light and concoctible, limpid and thin in reſpect of quality, ſweet and grateful to the taſte, and moſt proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the beſt of waters: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is an exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, although
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1997:42"/>the thinneſt part of all other waters extracted by the power of the ſun, as is evident; and becauſe of its uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall collection and commixture with ayre and<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. eod. cap.</hi> qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propter ex omnibus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis hae ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimae pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſount, &amp; odorem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum pluvia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis aqua ha bet, eo quod ex plurimis congregata eſt ac per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixta ut ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsime pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſcat.</note> clouds, which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and ill aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; it is more eaſily diſpoſed to putreſaction, and not thought fit to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1997:43"/>bee uſed without correction, (that is to ſay) taken<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum opus habent ut decoqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, ac excolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſin mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus odorem pravum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, et rau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedines &amp; vocis gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de acce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere par eſt.</note> freſh boyled, and ſtrained according to the decree of the ancients, elſe it ſoone corrupts and breeds rauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or whorſneſſe in thoſe that drink it.<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hip. ſect. 3.</hi> pravae verò omnes quae ex nive &amp; glacie fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, ubi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ſemet con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reverint non am plius ad priſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram redeu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</note> Snow &amp; ice waters are all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, for when they are once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed, they never
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1997:43"/>returne to their former nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, but the cleareneſſe, levity, and ſweetneſſe, that is in them doth vaniſh, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving behind a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous ſubſtance, as is proved by this experiment. Take a veſſell of water, and keepe it till it be frozen, then ſet it in ſome
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1997:44"/>hot place till it bee diſſolved, then meaſure it againe, and you ſhall find it much leſſe in quantitie then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and will plainely appeare, that the lighteſt &amp; thinneſt parts are expired; and for this cauſe it is ſaid to bee morbificall,<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hip. lo. cit.</hi> atque de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis quidem quae ex im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bribus nivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie colligun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad hunc ſe res habet modum at verò calculo maxime tentantur, &amp; renum morbis, ac urinae ſtilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia et cex. endicum af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionibus corripiuntur herniae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ijs ſuboriuntur cujuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di aquas bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt.</note> and moſt apt to generate the ſtone in the bladder,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1997:44"/>ſtrangurie, paine of the hips, and ruptures, &amp; theſe are the effects in general: The ſame alſo happen to the drinkers of river waters, which by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with pooles, ditches, &amp; moores they obtaine an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien qualitie, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bificall; and the only cauſe of ſuch
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1997:45"/>difference is their various participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral mixtures, ſome qualities more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsive force, and therefore ſome are called ſalt, ſulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, aluminous, bituminous, and the like; others ſweet and cleare,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1997:45"/>others muddy and terreſtriall, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by their ſetlings, but all are cauſes of affliction to thoſe that drink them; yet ſome bodies ſhall bee more<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. li. de aere loc. &amp; aq. cap. 5.</hi> quod autem non omnibus conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo, quorum quidem al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus ſatis fluida eſt, ac ſana, &amp; veſica non ardens, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſtomachus veſica val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de coardeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, hi facile urinam eijciunt &amp; in veſica ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ipſis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatur.</note> able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt then others, as thoſe that have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally laxe and fluid bellies, and ſound bodies, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate reines and bladders; for ſuch
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1997:46"/>doe more eaſily &amp; ſpeedily pumpe it out againe, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving little reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; Contrarily where the belly is coſtive, hot, and fiery, the bladder muſt needs bee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected after the ſame manner, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it exceedeth a naturall temper, then the necke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the bladder is ſoon
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1997:46"/>inflamed, by w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> meanes the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the urine is hindered, or that which paſſeth, is the pureſt &amp; thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt part of the ſame, the thicker being left behind, of which there is a graduall collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of new mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which is dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contracted till it groweth large, hard, and ſtony,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1997:47"/>and by the courſe and preſſure of the urine in piſsing, the ſtone is forced into the necke of the blader, which hindereth the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of urine, and procureth extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and paine; inſomuch, as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren when they labour with this diſeaſe, doe rub, and ſcratch, and teare the ſecret
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1997:47"/>parts, as if there were the onely ſtopping of their urine; and it is a manifeſt ſigne of ſuch a diſpoſition, when as ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the urine comes forth ſo limpid &amp; cleare, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſteth a ſtay of the groſſe matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, the purer part being ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from it, as it is reported by <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemian</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:1997:48"/>beare</p>
            <p>— <hi>Nil ſpiſſius illâ Dum bibitur, nil clarius eſt dum mingitur, unde Conſtat quod mult as faeces in corpore linquat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus the ſtone is often begotten by the drinking of water, eſpecially when the bladder is ill diſpoſed; but in<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hip. ſect. 3.</hi> gignitur autem &amp; pueris ex lacte, ſi non ſalubre fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſed val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de calidum et vitioſum.</note> children it is often begot by the uſe of milke, if it bee not good and ſound, but hot and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1997:48"/>cholericke: For by this meanes it heateth the belly and bladder, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperates the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine; and in my opinion (ſaith <hi>Hippocrates</hi>) ſmall dilute Wine is more wholeſome for them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hipp. in eodem lib.</hi> et mea qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia praeſtat pueris vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maxime di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutum exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here cum nimirum venas mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus adurat &amp; refecit.</note> becauſe it doth not ſcortch and dry the veines ſo much. Thus I have ſhewed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1997:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, what wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are wholſome and dieteticall; as alſo thoſe that are unwholſome and morbificall: now wee are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how they are pharmaceuticall, and to bee uſed as medicaments.</p>
            <p>To the end that we may more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfie, it will
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1997:49"/>not bee vaine in our progreſſe, to caſt our eye backe upon the ſtreames that flow from minerals, &amp; more particularly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the miſchieſes of them; becauſe they are ſo highly advanced in the thoughts of ſome Phyſicians, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; upon what ground I know not, but ſure I am
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1997:50"/>that they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo eſteemed by any of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents in our facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, either Greeks, or Arabians, or learned moderns, ſome reſpect they give them, and chiefely in exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall uſe, by the way of baths, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the like, and yet not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily ſo to bee uſed, but with a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1997:50"/>great deale of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare hereafter, both in reſpect of tempers and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to which they are applyed: In ſo much as <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> or <hi>Galen</hi> tooke little notice of them, which doth imply the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regard they had of them or their uſe in medicine,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1997:51"/>either for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation or reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for which cauſe we will tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell amongſt the Arabians, to the end that wee may ſearch out the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and uſe of them more direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take our view from that learned <hi>Avicen</hi> of ſuch minerall ſprings, as are before no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1997:51"/>And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Chymiſts</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute ſulphur as one of the <hi>tria principia</hi> in mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, therefore wee will in the firſt place diſcover the nocuments of ſuch waters. As for their differences, they are as many as the minerals from whence they ſpring, and with which they are
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1997:52"/>mixed; but in generall all of them are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hurtfull and dangerous, exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally or internal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applyed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeciall indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, without which they are very obnoxious; after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I am now to ſhew.</p>
            <p>The nocuments
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:1997:52"/>of minerall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by potation or drinking, and eſpecially ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from ſulphur, are theſe, they<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Avicen tract 5</hi> Iſtae quidem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua adurunt humores &amp; eos putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt, quare ſequuntur in principio febres cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tericae poſtea in fiae fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholicae, propter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſtionem ſanguinis ex ets factum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> et mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus quidem humor qui ex hujus modi aquis generatur, eſt humor melancholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus malus qui nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur cholera nigra, &amp;c.</note> ſcortch and putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the humors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get cholericke fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, which alter &amp; are changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to melancholicke, by reaſon of adu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the blood, &amp; this melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke humor thus
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1997:53"/>generated is called aduſt choler, and is the worſt of all melancholy: Moreover the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that come of drinking ſuch wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, are inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the eyes, jaundies, hot rhumes, difficultie in piſsing, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of the whole body.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Avicen.</hi> nocumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum iſtarum aquarum eſt ſtipricare et conſtringere naturam, &amp; exaſperare pectus &amp; vocem &amp; cauſare difficulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem urinae &amp; ſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere vias cibi et cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſare corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris maciem.</note> Aluminous waters are aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:1997:53"/>generally, and they exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the breaſt, cauſe a difficultie of urine, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the body.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="o" place="margin">nocumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum iſtarum eſt compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ex no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumento a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae alumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſae et no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumento aquae ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phureae, &amp;c</note> Vitriall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of alume and ſulphur, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the effects are anſwerable to both in reſpect of ſtiptication &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperation, as alſo in aduſtion and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:1997:54"/>putrefaction of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="p" place="margin">nocumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum iſtius aquae eſt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite nocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phureae.</note> Al ſprings from ſilver ſhould ſeem cordial according to the vaine appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar: Nevertheleſſe by the ſame autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they make up the number of morbifical cauſes, and the ſpeciall nocuments are to ulcerate the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:1997:54"/>are anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thoſe of ſulphur: So alſo are thoſe waters which<note n="q" place="margin">nocumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum iſtius aquae eſt ſi mile etiam nocumento aquae ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phureae ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joris nocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti quam illud, &amp;c.</note> ſpring from green braſſe, ſaving that the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments are grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then of ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, violently o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the orifice of the veines, by which doth hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen piſsing and ſpitting of blood, and bloody fluxes,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:1997:55"/>all being excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding dangerous, and theſe are the qualities of them, &amp; effects inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken, either as meate or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine. Now let us conſider their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments external<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applyed, as by way of bathing and the like.</p>
            <p>Bathing in ſalt waters is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what allowed by
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:1997:55"/>
               <hi>Avicen,</hi> where he affirmeth it to bee good to cure the itch and ſcabs; and<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hip. ſect. 3.</hi> ſunt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men naturae quaedam et morbi, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus tales a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae potu ſunt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modae.</note> 
               <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall hee proteſteth againſt them, and doth abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prohibit their uſe internally, yet (ſaith hee) the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe may require ſuch a remedy, by which is to bee
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:1997:56"/>underſtood ſome extraordinary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and after a moſt ſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to bee uſed: And ſo alſo may other compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of minerals be uſed; yet <hi>Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen</hi> conceiveth it to bee ſomewhat doubtfull, and (however) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie to be worſe then the diſeaſe; for (ſaith he)<note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Avieen. tract. 4.</hi> aqua ſalſa in balneo confert ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biei et pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritui, verum careſacit cutem po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtea conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat, et quum non fuerit pruritus, tunc ipſa facit acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere pruri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:1997:56"/>it bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of itch and ſcabs, ſo it is apt to generate the ſame in thoſe that are cleare and ſound, by reaſon of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſation and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification of the skin; beſides it withereth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, hurts the eyes, diſturbes the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and cauſeth ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharrs &amp; rhumes;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:1997:57"/>ſo as (if it be well conſidered) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy is more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious then the diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="t" place="margin">aqua alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minoſa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſat cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringit ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam.</note> Bathing in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminous waters, condenſeth &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringeth the skin, cauſeth ephemeral fevers, cramps and convulſions, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in cleane bodies.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="u" place="margin">aqua ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurea &amp; neptica cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexionem cut is corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris et praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat ipſam ad putredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem et facit accidere ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarrhas,</note> Baths of ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurious and bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuminous
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:1997:57"/>waters, ſpoile the comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the body, and diſpoſe it to putrifaction and rhumes; and if they continue in ſuch a bath long it doth threaten a dropſie, but a jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice doth more frequently follow. The minerall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of iron are thought to be leaſt hurtfull of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:1997:58"/>minerals, and yet of little uſe amongſt the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents for medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Thus I have waded, through fountaines, pools, motes, moores, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and as farre into the ſea as I dare, or as is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and have ſhewed both ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:1997:58"/>uſe, and effects; by which deſcription every man may know how to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh for uſe, thoſe that are whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, from thoſe which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſome, and morbificall; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo how and after what manner they hurt, being taken into the body ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camentally,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:1997:59"/>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeciall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; as alſo by their outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication; and all this confirmed by the doctrine &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the moſt learned and anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent doctors, and parents of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine. Now it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth that I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the world with a new mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſpring, un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heard
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:1997:59"/>of before, and lately practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amongſt us in our owne County of Norfolke; and although it be yet unknown to ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, yet it is very adventurouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly practiſed againſt both rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and all autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. For in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:1997:60"/>to bee a flat confutation of all, both ancient and moderne, as it is uſed and adviſed, the manner wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of I intend to ſet downe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it with the former grounds; as alſo with thoſe which are more recent, by which it will appeare, either that mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall waters differ
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:1997:60"/>this yeare from thoſe of old, or elſe that our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe is either more learned or more raſh.</p>
            <p>The ſpring it ſelfe riſeth out of a clift naked, and unſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt the ſea, and is imbraced and often covered by the raging oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, by which it obtayneth ſome mixture, both of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:1997:61"/>ſubſtance and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity from the ſame, which is not the leaſt of our obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, ſince it doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duce much to the ill or well diſpoſing of the matter for uſe: the drinkers of the ſame have beene many, and they report ſome of them that it taſteth harſh and like ruſt of iron, others
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:1997:61"/>taſte it like inke, and all thinke it a miracle, that by the infuſion of a nutgaule it doth turnered, &amp; alter the colour: To be ſhort, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of practiſe is thus adviſed, and appointed by a Phyſician who is thought to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and hee had need to bee ſo, to make good the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturous,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:1997:62"/>and confident adviſing ſuch a remedie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo ſmall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, which if <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> may bee judge<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hip lib. de priſca medicina.</hi> quandoqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem naturae cegnitio mini medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co eſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaria vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur iſque omni ſludio deber con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendare (ſi modo quod recte prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlare volet) ut ir telligat quonam mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do quis ad ca quae co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meduntur et bibuntur ſe habent, &amp;c.</note> will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to bee a fault. Moreover this ſpaw (as it is named by the chief Phyſician thereof) is reſolutely deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to be from a minerall, but of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:1997:62"/>what mixture is yet diſputable, and therefore the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe ought to bee the more doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be received into the body: For which cauſe our learned coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-man of the bath in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of minerall waters,<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Iorden.</hi>
               </note> although his affection to ſuch ſprings, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:1997:63"/>him of much good uſe, that may be made of them, and great benefit to man in curing diſeaſes if they were inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his feare of ſome mixture with other wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which may iſſue into them, for this cauſe only hee proteſts hee dares not adviſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:1997:63"/>the inward uſe of them; yet this our ſpaw lies more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to ſuch mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then the bath, and a worſe mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from the ſea, yet wee will not feare to drinke, and adviſe it to be drunke by pottles at one time and in the morning cold and faſting, as alſo in the open ayre, crude and raw
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:1997:64"/>from the ſpring, contrary to the practiſe of all that ever, were ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; and this courſe every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to continue for the ſpace of thirtie or fourtie dayes, and it is ſaid to cure all diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, without any other conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: So that if we examin this ſpring and the practiſe of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:1997:64"/>it, wee cannot but ſee a direct oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of all the ancients. But ſo it fares with too much confidence, as the Tragedian ſpeakes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Aio, nego, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ratio mibi conſtat ulla, cur aiam aut negem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this may appeare, it is needfull that wee
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:1997:65"/>compare this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and opinion with the practiſe of thoſe times, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in this thing; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if it were but what it is by ſome thought to bee, it were then the complement of all medicine, which the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt Phyſicians never yet compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:1997:65"/>the vulgar claime power to make every wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a phyſician, without either ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die or learning, or authority from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny univerſitie; and thinke it a light matter to bee a<note n="x" place="margin">facile qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eſt eſſe medicum ſed bonum medicum eſſe difficil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limum, ne dicam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsibile.</note> Phyſician; yet thoſe that are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, never found it ſo eaſie a matter, <hi>Quolibet ex ligno
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:1997:66"/>non fit Mercurius.</hi> True it is, there are ſome which can act the carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of phyſicians, as Players doe the perſons of Kings and Lords, and yet are none, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hipp.li.de leg.</hi> quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum enim illi quidem formam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum &amp; perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m byſtriones referant.</note> 
               <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates.</hi> But to make good our undertakings, and to ſhew the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of our ſpaw-practiſe from that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:1997:66"/>of old, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is called learned: <hi>Avicen</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Avicen. tract. 5. cap. 1.</hi> potus pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae aquae nocet tribus modis, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nous eſt, quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitat cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatem na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalem in nembris, et lebilitat membra principalia, quare accidit eis tuno debilitas vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum quatuor naturalium, membris autem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentalibus accidit debilitas motuum et tremor; ſecundus modus eſt quod virtus ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative in hepate debilitatur in ſequeſtrando omnem aquoſitatem a ſanguine, quare aut effu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur aquoſitas ad partes inter mirach et ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fach accidit hydropiſis aquoſa: aut penetrat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoſitas cum ſanguine ad membra &amp; accidit hydropiſis carnoſo et virtus ſequeſtrativa inre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus debilitature, qutaex eomictus urinae ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voluatarlus cum difficultate in ed, et debilitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur renes.</note> affirmeth the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of waters in generall to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitate naturall heate, enervate the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:1997:67"/>inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, deject the appetite, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the liver: but this our ſpaw is ſaid to incite appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, temper natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heate, inliven the members, and rectifie the liver. <hi>Hippocrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hipp. Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len. Avicen li. citat.</note> 
               <hi>Galen, Avicen,</hi> ſay all with one conſent, that the drinking of waters cold and raw, unboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:1997:67"/>unſtrayned, or uncorrected, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though otherwiſe they be not of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, yet that ſuch drinking doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the ſpleene, and ſwell and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the ſubſtance of the ſame: but contrary to this, we ſay, our ſpaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water drunke in large quantities, cold &amp; raw from the ſpring, doth
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:1997:68"/>diminiſh, ſoften, and cure the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the ſpleen; and by its mineral qualitie (if it were well knowne) is able to performe greater cures then theſe, to which I ſhall anſwer more fully in our fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe, when I diſcover the opinions of ſome moderne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:1997:68"/>of minerall waters cold and raw.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Avicen. loc. citat. Hipp.</hi> at vero calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo maxime renian ur er renum morbis ac urinae ſtilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaio.</note> Moreover the ſaid authors affirme the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of water to generate waterie dropſies, the ſtone and ſtrangurie, with other diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in ſuch as have imperfect and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered reines: but this our Spaw is preſcribed as a ſpeciall remedie
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:1997:69"/>againſt the ſame difficultie of urine, the ſtone &amp; drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Avicen tract. 5.</hi> aqua bibita in iejunio debilitat ſtomachum &amp; facit ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidere ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarrhas in frigidan do cerebrum propter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſum ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machi cum cerebro, &amp; propter aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoſorum, nocet enim in frigidan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do hepar et ſplenem &amp; preparat ad hydropiſim, &amp;c.</note> Matutine or morning drinking of water (ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicen</hi>) doth debili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the ſtomacke, breedeth rhumes, and refrigerateth the braine over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much by conſent with the ventricle, as alſo by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of waterie vapors, and refri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerating
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:1997:69"/>the liver and ſpleene, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid dropſies: but our Spaw-water drunke early in the morning, and cold, cornforts the heart, ſtrengthens the ſtomacke, and ſo by conſent the head, liver, and ſpleene. They al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the drinking of no waters, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther freſh, ſalt, alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:1997:70"/>bitumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous or ſulphure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to bee whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. de ſanit. tuen. lib. 6 cap. 9.</hi> Si tamen ipſis uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quae ut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dulces ſunt: quod utile etiam aliqui ex ipſis p ove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niat, id vero nen perinde tuto dixeris.</note> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I incline ſomewhat to an exact correction, yet <hi>Avicen,</hi> maketh queſtion whether minerall waters will admit of any or not<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Avicen.</hi> rectificatio iſtarum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarum ſi poſsibile eſt.</note>: but they were ignorant of the vertue of our Spaw, for this is to be drunk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:1997:70"/>any prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as if <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans cautela</hi> were hereticall in this our nimble age. Notwithſtanding they were not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of them, as will appeare by <hi>Galen,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. loc. citato.</hi> ſatius au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi equas expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientia diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceraere: quando eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am rarae inventu ſunt.</note> when as hee renders a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his diſlike, which is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of their mixture, and ſuch (ſaith hee) as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:1997:71"/>not be diſcovered or found out o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then by experience, and experience is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hipp. aph. 1.</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culoſa.</note> (ſaith <hi>Hippocrates</hi>) the reaſon is taken from the dignitie of the ſubject, which is the body of man, upon which ſuch expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments are tried: And for this cauſe <hi>Galen</hi> was feareful
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:1997:71"/>of their uſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee may grant ſomething to be profitable in them, as there is in every creature, in reſpect of their qualities, ſo they be rightly prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and applyed; yet (ſaith he)<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.loc.citato.</hi> Id vero non perinde tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to dixeris.</note> let no man ſay they are ſafe, or the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of them; not that the ancients were ſo ignorant
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:1997:72"/>of their qualities,<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.loc.citato.</hi> Calidarum autem quae ſponte aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us his uſat eſt: ſiqui dem quae ſulphuroſae bituminoſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae propterca quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miciſsimae calida na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliter capiti ſunt.</note> (as ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Chymiſt;</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) neither doe I conceive any great difficultie to prove their <hi>nova medicina</hi> to be but as a new cape ſet upon an old cloak, as alſo that mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals were as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed one from an other, in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:1997:72"/>of name, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and mixture, as alſo firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond qualities, as they have beene by any <hi>Chymiſt;</hi> Although I am not ignorant of <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus, Arnoldus, Lullius, Crollius, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gric. &amp; Libavius,</hi> which by way of explication, and laborious operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, have made it ſomewhat more
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:1997:73"/>cleare in ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and practiſe. And yet all is but a dilatation or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of an old foundation of the ancients, and no abſolute new edifice of their owne, as ſome of them pretend. But however, becauſe this practiſe of drinking minerall waters in our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey (I ſuppoſe) is
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:1997:73"/>chiefely incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by, and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon our own learned countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Bath,<note place="margin">Doxtor lorden.</note> who is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to any Phyſician; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it will not be amiſſe to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his opinion concerning the uſe of minerall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and whether the drinking of them may bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:1997:74"/>after the manner of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Spaw; that is, to be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the body cold and raw. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee were much devoted to the uſe of them, yet he adviſeth the externall uſe only in bathing, when as he ſaith we find many of theſe to be venemous and deadly, as procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:1997:74"/>from Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke Sandaracha, Cadinia, and the like; therefore we had need bee very warie in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward uſe of them, &amp; therefore <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes</hi> well in <hi>Tara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina</hi> was found to be ſo deadly, as that for this cauſe it was ſtopped up; by <hi>Montpellier</hi> at <hi>Perant</hi> is a well which kils all the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:1997:75"/>fowles that drinke of it, the lake <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernus</hi> kils all the fowles that fly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it, ſo doe the vapours ariſing from <hi>Carons</hi> den, betweene <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Puteolum,</hi> ſo there are divers waters in <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Rhetia</hi> which breed ſwellings in the throat, others proceeding from <hi>Gipſum</hi> doe ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:1997:75"/>But where we find waters to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome minerals, and ſuch as are convenient &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and upon good ſearch, and long experience found to bee ſo, there we may bee bold to uſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:1997:76"/>doe not imagine them to bee ſuch abſolute remedies, as that they are of themſelves able to cure diſeaſes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either rule for the uſe of them, or without other helpe adjoyning to them: Moreover the ſaid Doctor doth confeſſe, that although the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Bath in Somerſetſhiere,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:1997:76"/>in his owne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion bee the moſt abſolute and wholſome of all others, &amp; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth as whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome as any to bee taken into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yet (ſaith hee) the jealoſie I have of their alien mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with other vvaters adjoyning, doth deterre mee from the counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their invvard
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:1997:77"/>uſe, and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of them any other wayes, then by bathing. But if any adventure to drinke of ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſtreames, he deſireth them to be drunke hot by any meanes, both for the better pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netration, and leſſe offence to the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, then when they are taken crude &amp; cold pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:1997:77"/>for proofe the ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians &amp; Romans, which drank moſt of their wine and water hot, and not cold &amp; raw from the ſpring, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of our Spaw in Norfolke: Thus it appeares that neither ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor modern do much affect the practiſe
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:1997:78"/>of drinking any water, except up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch ſtrict and warie termes and circumſtances, as rarely or never will concurre. But however the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the water cold is abſolutely prohibited, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to reaſon and antiquity: ſo that it muſt appeare, that the ground of this our practiſe,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:1997:78"/>and the uſe of this our minerall ſpring is precipiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; dangerous, as hath bin plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved, both out of the ancients &amp; alſo many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned modernes; yet ſuch is the vanity of our age, as that<note n="i" place="margin">Audax omnia per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peti Gens humana ruit per ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titum nefas. <hi>Horat.</hi> Nitimur in votitum ſemper cu pimuſque negata.</note> prohibition is the greateſt ſpurre to praecipitation, and doth hurrie us into miſchiefes
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:1997:79"/>forbidden, as alſo cauſe us <hi>Narciſſus.</hi> like to dote upon our own ſuppoſed perfection, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending (if wee may be our owne judges) our reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and learned fathers, as if wee were not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> nay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as hee vaunts himſelfe in the Poet;<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Homer. <hi>Tydides me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier patie.</hi> Horat.</note> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:1997:79"/>in our own ſtrength wee are ready to blemiſh them with do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, thinking, thoſe learned fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of medicine too old, and not wiſe enough to teach us; when wiſe men know we are too young to ſound their depthes without their owne lines; For when wee
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:1997:80"/>have done all our beſt, even then we are compelled to acknowledge the truth of that ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſentence of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that our lives are too ſhort to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the extent of art; and for this cauſe I thinke my ſelfe bound to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire that &amp; thoſe which I cannot
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:1997:80"/>comprehend, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his judgement in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> upon a book of <hi>Heraclitus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And although I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be wiſe alone then erre with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, yet in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects I proclaime with <hi>Epiphanius Ferdinandus, Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem errare cum Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leno &amp; Hippocrate quam cum omnibus alijs ſapere,</hi> not
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:1997:81"/>that I adore any mortall more then by a venerable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme which is their due; and it were facriledge to rob them of it. But to returne to our ſubject, mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtreames have ſome toleration in externall uſe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for bathes; and not ſo neither without ſpeciall indication and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification;
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:1997:81"/>but for the wanton courſe of drinking them after ſuch an irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall manner, it was never counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced by any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, or learned moderne; For my owne part I could wiſh there were ſome ſuch <hi>Nectar</hi> ſtreames, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſed after the manner of our Spaw, might not
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:1997:82"/>onely cure all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, but alſo waſh off that curſe of mortalitie, changing age into youth (as <hi>Medea</hi> is fabled to have done) infirmities into perfection,<note place="margin">Aeſonidem mutaſſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim &amp;c. <hi>Ovid. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</hi>
               </note> and weakenes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtrength; and on this condition, who would not ſhake hands with <hi>Galen</hi> and all the reſt, and breake up
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:1997:82"/>ſchooles of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke? for why ſhould ſtudents ſmother themſelus in their ſtudies, when they might ſit upon a clift and thence view<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 107 24.</hi> Neptunnm procule ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ ſpectare fureatem. <hi>Horat.</hi>
               </note> the wonders of the deepe, and drinke immortall health at ſo cheape a rate? And as I heartily deſire to taſte of ſuch, ſo I abhorre the uſe of thoſe
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:1997:83"/>that have contrary effects; as to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt them that are ſound, to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thoſe that are ſtrong, to haſten age in thoſe that are young, and in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion to ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle and ſwallow up all in death; And ſuch have bin the effects of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall wels and fountaines, as is expreſt in our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:1997:83"/>diſcourſe, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially uſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch caution and circumſtance, as is laid downe by learned and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete practiſers. And they are ſuch alſo as can hardly or never bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled in one object. Therefore both out of my ſpeciall affection to my friends, and charitie to my op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:1997:84"/>(if there be any ſuch) but<note n="n" place="margin">Patria u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na omnes omnium charitates complecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all in love to my Countrey, I have endeavoured to acquaint thoſe that are not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in theſe things (although other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe learned) with the danger of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne things, both in reſpect of their mixture and manner of uſing ſo raſhly: For raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:1997:84"/>hath bin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of old, and caution never knowne to hurt,<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Epicharimu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> nay to bee the very ſinnewes of wiſedome. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, when I ſee <hi>Galen</hi> &amp; others ſo ſtrict in ſmaller matters prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the uſe of rain water (which is little differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from the beſt of waters) I cannot but bee
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:1997:85"/>zealous in matters of ſuch great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward uſe of mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall waters with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any extraction or correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or ſo much as colation, which is the eaſieſt of all other prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; Moreover if any ſhal ſay there is ſuch perfect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colation through the earth, as alſo ſuch ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:1997:85"/>of heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall qualities, that they ſtand in need of no better it will ſoon be anſwered, that they are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ignorant, both of their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, qualities, &amp; uſe; neither did they ever take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the ſweats &amp; labours, which many learned <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> have taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:1997:86"/>of thoſe mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, from whence the waters of this kind receive their tincture. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, were they in themſelves ſweet, light, thin, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either ſapor or odor, and pleaſant as wine, yet the large drinking of them cold, is moſt contrary to reaſon and all ſound au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:1997:86"/>proved. But that I may now avoid prolixity, I wil ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to ſhoare, and to conclude, am bound to adviſe a ſerious meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this ſubject, as a moſt neceſſary conſideration, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a maine cauſe of health or ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of divers kinds. Therefore I have plainly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the nature and
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:1997:87"/>difference of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by reaſon of their ſeverall mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome &amp; unwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome earth, &amp; ſuch as have beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes eſteemed &amp; uſed both in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et &amp; medicine for ſound and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, all being confirmed by the practiſe &amp; judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the moſt learned &amp; ancient
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:1997:87"/>Phyſicians; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding I have left a libertie to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding agent, to make uſe of all as they may bee ſtrictly &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly indicated, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe upon a meere logicall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or ſome nice diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe thereof (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) is to bee prohibited. Not that I undervalew
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:1997:88"/>the true uſe of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke, as a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid to all arts &amp; ſciences, but the exceſſe which is the eſſence of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. Beſides phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians are ſenſible artificers, and not onely referre all to ſenſe, but alſo are chiefly taught by ſenſible precepts, and therefore <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinus</hi> by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Galen</hi>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:1997:88"/>condemnes diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, definitions and diviſions that are too logicall as cauſes of confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, rather then ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid inſtruction, For which cauſe I have laboured to be the <hi>Eccho</hi> of thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, rather then the parent of my owne invention and judgement.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
